all right hello it is May 16th 2024
we're in the RX and fur JL project with
some guests from bias lab and
participants and vzer will be sharing
with us about the RX environments. JL
package so thanks all for joining
looking forward to this presentation and
discussion go for
it all right thank you Daniel uh so my
name is V I am a second year PhD student
in bias lab uh you may know Bas laab
because we are the uh main authors of
the RX infer package a package for
reactive Beijing
inference and last year when I was
working with RX and fur um and doing
well reactive beijan inference I found
that there was a a lacking support for
environments in the same reactive
Paradigm uh and we were relying on
reinforcement learning uh packages such
as gymnasium or or reinforcement
learning
and I didn't really like it so I wrote
RX environments. JL a package for
reactive um environments which aims to
uh complement RX and fur in the
reactive um agent
development um ecosystem so if we look
at RX environments it's a very
lightweight boiler plate package it
contains a boiler plate code to make
something that I call a reactive
environment a reactive environment is
a an environment that consists of
entities where an entity can be an agent
but it can also be a component of an
environment or the entire environment
itself and what we have to describe is
how entities communicate with each other
so every entity has its own Mark of
blanket with with which it can
communicate with other entities in the
environment so in that sense it's very
um related to active inference because
well
we have a very specific notion of the
interior of an entity and the exterior
of the entity and it's Mark of blanket
and I try to replicate that in ARX
environments so um to give a short demo
we can dive right into the code I have
prepared um the mountain car example in
the uh documentation of ARX environments
but just to Showcase to you that this
gives you um more
um flexibility to work with so we have
on the left hand side I have my code
because I'm going to manipulate this
environment uh in real time and on the
right hand side I have the environment
so I have my landscape I hope you guys
can see my cursor by the way uh I have
the landscape and in the middle I have
one agent one car a DOT representing a
car um what's nice about RX environments
is that I can send um actions to the
environment so my landscape the
environment is one entity the agent the
car is a different entity and I can send
a command that contains Engine Force on
a scale from minus one to one so I can
send uh minus one to The Entity and
you'll see that the car starts driving
up the hill it doesn't have a lot of
Engine Force and I can live send
different commands and you'll
see that the car responds accordingly
now what's nice about arcs environments
is that as I said uh you'll get native
uh multi-agent environments out of the
box so if I just add a different agent
Mountain car agent with some hyper
parameters to the
environment you'll see that there is now
a second dot at the bottom of the valley
a second car and similar to how this
first car can be
controlled we can control the second car
too 01 was
maybe uh this uh I should have maybe
given this car a bit less engine power
because it's clearly flying off the
screen um but you get the gist um that
we
can um well control both cars
simultaneously um and RX environments
handles all this uh this communication
natively reactively under the hood so my
idea is or my next steps for this
project are going to be to uh
incorporate better into the ARX and fur
ecosystem because I think that building
agents uh with ARs environments in this
way U that both the active inference
Community as well as the arcs Ander
Community can can can benefit from this
so this is a very short overview of the
things that ARX environments can do it
can do a whole lot more um but I think
that this is a very short demo that
gives you the best idea of why it's nice
that we're going to go reactive because
you get stuff like this we can control
in real time we can control multi-agent
environments um and it's very um active
inference e in that sense so on that
note um I'll stop sharing my
screen let's see and um yeah if you guys
have any questions about this which I uh
which I heard you have then I'll be very
happy to take
it awesome
thanks very informative and hilarious
Mountain car example yeah this this you
you you can play with this Engine Force
of this mountain car and I probably
should have prepared that it doesn't fly
off the screen but you I mean it gets
the point for us right
it's yeah okay um I'll share screen and
just type and so everyone else in the
group just go for asking any of the
questions we'd already identified or any
new questions arising so go for
it um interested Rel
between I I I don't understand you very
well maybe there's do you understand c
as well okay
relationship
between you're you're very very
faint uh yeah okay
well with stuff I I actually had a
question do not on this particular page
that um Daniel's sharing right now I
tried my hand at let's say plugging in
the mountain car the existing Mountain
car agent in the RX and thir
documentation into your Mountain car
environment I wasn't quite able to do
that but it appears that you you have
done that uh in that example just then
and then maybe I was missing something
because in the in the documentation the
RX environments documentation from
mounting car I didn't see that there was
a an agent that had you know
instantiated the generative model uh
much in the same way that the ARX infer
documentation had and I thought oh okay
this this is a wrapper or you know a
nice API for me to specify an
environment I I now have to go away and
then specify my agent also but it seems
is that what you did for that example
just then or or did you just no no I
just for this example just now I just
used my um you
know custom commands that I just uh sent
myself um so this is something that I'm
actively working on on uh combining the
two um the mountain active inference
Mountain car example on the ARX and fur
website I believe is a bit
um cheating in a sense because we give
it all Environ Dynamics all functions of
the environment Dynamics and then we uh
do some uh some approximation to the
posterior of what we have to do but in a
sense it doesn't really discover that it
has to do anything because it knows all
the environment Dynamics so that's why I
haven't really spent time on um
incorporating this specific example
because I feel that if we're going to
demo this package plus an agent that it
should be an agent that actually has
capabilities of exploring the
environment instead of knowing all the
environment Dynamics and just while
basically doing model predictive
control right okay that makes it a bit
clearer okay I I have a follow up maybe
let somebody else um something just for
now thank you very
much so to give a very short answer to
your question we can we can sit together
if we uh on if want to Define an agent a
generative model I know how to hoop the
two up I just don't have a working
example
yet right okay I have I don't want to
use this I don't want to use this agent
from from the arxs and F documentation
because indeed I feel that it's a bit
cheating but it's my personal opinion
right yeah yeah okay that that actually
clears a lot of things off for me
because I was kind of unclear like oh do
I do I kind of plug that one in is that
is that what I do yeah okay but that's
not that functionality exactly CLE yeah
we can um however there is a a subtlety
there and that is something that I find
very interesting in my research is if
you open up this space or you open up
your environment to be reactive then you
want your environment to be able to um
receive an action at any point in time
so what we see in reinforcement learning
is that you have a specific transition
function the environment Waits until you
send an action it will move the
environment forward a pre-specified
amount of time and it will emit to you
an observation and a reward however if
you make this entire thing reactive then
well our agent would be able to emit at
any point in time and also it would be
able to get an observation at any point
in time now that is a very
interesting um setting to work with
because now our agents should kind of be
robust to getting an observation at any
point in time specifically what if uh
our agent that lives on some embedded
device on some drone whatsoever it has
less compute to do to do inference
however well at some point we're going
to have to send an observ or an agent an
action back to the environment we're
going to have to do something so this
reactivity opens
up uh a research Avenue for well right
now for me because I find find this very
interesting on how reactive truly
reactive agents would look like if you
see what I mean yeah yeah I do that's
that's exceptionally exciting stuff it's
it's awesome um okay but but okay just
just to wrap up my my yes question there
is no at the moment you kind of manually
you know yes you put in the force limit
and you say okay I'm going to kind of
manually you know play around with
letters and I have I have working
examples with like ban therat or very
very easy um which I probably I don't
know if I have them on my machine right
now or if they live somewhere like it
works but the the thing that I got to
work is model predictive control and not
active inference yet so that's
why awesome all right thank
you you're welcome
um is my yeah can you hear me a bit
better now yes okay but um I'm uh
interested in the relationship between
orx environments and orex in fur um for
example to put it simply is it possible
to use only orx environments or is it
supposed to be always be used in
collaboration with RX and
fur
us yes the relation is that uh I wrote
ARX environment
specifically um as a complimentary
package to ARX and fur so if you just
want to do basian inference you use ARX
and fur but I think if you want to build
agents that you're better off using the
the two together so RX environments
is um a package that uses the same
reactive backend as RX and fur so it's
made to be compatible with ARX and fur
however if you write um agents just with
an algorithm you can use ARX
environments by itself it's not
mandatory to use ARX and fur they are
separate packages there's not a
dependency on ARX Ander however since um
they share the same reactive back endend
so the same package for reactivity under
the hood which is also from bias laab
which is rocket um if you want to build
agents I would advise to to use RX INF
fur so there they're disjoined but
they're designed with each other in mind
or ARX environments is designed with ARX
Ander in
mind so um if we um use this high level
of a
of abstraction given to us by ARX Vons
uh do we lose
anything uh or can we at any time dive
into the lower levels by means of orex
INF fur
itself
so um I would say yes because the
inference process that happens in ARX
and fur is disjointed from what's going
on in ARX environment similarly to well
what happens in in in real life so you
can you can see ARX environments as a
package in which you can make
um like a digital twin of the
environment but then whatever happens in
the inference process in your agents
well that's still RX andur like all RX
andur um diagnostic tools or debuging
tools should be available
there um and a more practical question I
know from based on the large papers um
and uh Professor def as well they like
to divide the um what's going on into
these six methods the ACT future execute
observe compute and slide so do you see
that as kind of Superfluous in the orx
orx environment setting
or um is it is it fine to use that
apprach
let me Google the definition for
Superfluous uh ah um that is a I'm going
to spread very carefully in answering
that questions uh I don't think it is
Superfluous um because in a sense that
it's if you want to design your agent
such that it goes through those steps um
then you're more than welcome to uh my
personal opinion is that I'm I will I'm
going to try and see if I can make an
active inference agent that does
inference in one step instead of having
to act
observe uh plan slide uh and so forth
however for AR environment so for your
environment it doesn't really matter how
you will get to your uh to your action
as long as well or not right you can you
can send an action at any point in time
and if you don't send an action the
world will just continue that and arcs
environments will just continue running
there's no real constraints on that so
that the design is to be as less
constraining on on users as possible
while opening up this reactivity uh
um the reactivity aspect and also for
um if you start with the package you
could make what I call discreet
environments they're they're a bit
feeding I would say because they're
basically just the arc environment's
equivalent of a of a classical
reinforcement learning environment where
you have a prespecify time step every
time but I wanted to make that to make
the transition easier because if you go
full reactive right off the bat I would
say it's a very ambitious thing to
do so I don't think I don't think it's a
Superfluous
algorithm
um but I I also don't think it's a
um
well our environment doesn't constrain
you to use it so I would
say nice now let's say uh one has a need
to write one's own node in the
factory um put ARX environments support
that kind of thing or is it kind of an
irrelevant
question it's it's in that sense I would
say irrelevant because uh the um a
custom node is something that lives in
ARX and fur um and ARX environments
really uh is concerned with everything
that goes on outside of your inference
process um then another quick question
while playing with the um I think it was
a thermostat problem in oric
environments I wanted to see the time
behavior of some variables like
observations States controls um free
energy and things like that but it
wasn't straightforward to me how to plot
those um in the arment settings uh is
there uh an example that you can point
as to or a fragment of code that shows
us how to do
that um I can make it because I I know
how I can access so free energy is uh
something that lives inside your agent
so it's part of the inference process
it's the you know it's the uh cost
function if you will of of of the
inference process so for free energy you
would have to look at your uh would have
to look into ARX and fur however
everything that goes on in our
environments we can extract it and we
can plot it so both uh environment
States as well as emitted controls uh or
observations uh we can extract all those
things um I can show a code
fragment that does this because it's
well one line um however I also
understand that that is not something
that
uh well you probably remember after this
meeting so I'll I'll make sure that uh
we can design a
uh uh an example that showcases this but
in uh in a nutshell we can uh create a
keep actor so this is a well uh an
entity that will keep all everything
that it gets
uh we'll keep it inside memory and then
we subscribe to the observations of the
agent so we say well subscribe to
observations and with this Ops keep
actor uh we do
this and if I then call OBS
values this will contain all kinds of
well ARS environment
observations which is basically a
wrapper struct for uh let
me call data on this entire
array and you'll get your individual
observation so we can basically tap
anywhere in this process uh anywhere in
this communication we can we can tap
whatever is being emitted so if I run
this again now it will contain 400
elements because well this environment
is reactively running while we speak so
the the the agent is getting more and
more observations so you see this thing
reactively growing every time I call
uh or extract its uh its contents so
there is definitely functionality in
which you can sort of inspect this
process um but yeah I I I have to stress
that it's really distinct from the
inference process so if you make an
agent in ARX infer and you hook it up to
ARX envir ments then you have to set up
a similar procedure to extract free
energy and stuff like that um from ARX
and fur um and because I'm not the
author of ARX and fur I I don't know how
easy that is um but for AR environments
I yeah this is one of the first things
that I wanted to do see what my agent
was sending see what my agent was
observing so I made sure to build
it yeah I'm not sure if what you just
showed was uh recorded by us so if you
could uh just make sure that that is
included in your examples as well that
would yes that that's my idea that we
can uh or I I just wanted to Showcase uh
for now such that you can so that you
know that it exists but it wasn't meant
to be well a big tutorial or anything I
can just put it in the examples and uh
uh yeah then then we can plot it that's
that's not a problem
okay thanks a
lot you're
welcome okay anyone else can go for a
question or we have some other written
ones or I can ask a
question um I have a quick question I
would just wonder once I don't know if
you guys can hear me I hope so yes um
fantastic um a lot of the examples that
uh you have there and kind of the way
I'm I'm probably naive in how I'm
thinking about this um the ARX
environment is modeling something in the
real world um or at least that's the
example that we're thinking of right now
um is the is arc's environments capable
of essentially
modeling um more metaphysical spaces so
if you think
of your question in a way that you have
a Time series or a space that you're
trying to
occupy but it's not a physical space
it's a more theoretical space uh you
know dimensionality that you're trying
to have an agent
navigate um is that something that this
that you see that this
is you know usable for or is this
something that we need to kind of gear
back towards the arent for um package
itself to kind of build the more
metaphysical concept of the environment
that you're putting together does that
make sense so yeah if I understand your
question
correctly um yeah I my answer to that
would be that there's no a physics
simulator or whatever in arcs
environments it's purely the boiler
plate to make whatever you write act
reactively uh and expose reactive
streams that you can then use in arcs
and
so um for example one of our colleagues
has made a an
environment that Returns the um the
result of a stochastic differential
equation so an agent could query with an
action I want the realization at time T
and the environment would respond with
the actual value um and with this
interplay of query in a stochastic
differential equation and uh and getting
a result you can cast solving a
differential stochastic differential
equation sort of a uh aasan stat based
model uh I'm not an expert on this topic
I just know that one of our colleagues
uh did this so if I understand your
question correctly that would be the
sort of environments you were after or
you were you were questioning about um
so I would say yes you can so there's no
there's no physics simulator or anything
in there because that's a whole
different uh a whole different topic um
my main thing was just to make whatever
code you guys write to make it
reactive fantastic thank you now that
makes a lot of sense I just wanted to
clarify that since no it's
perfect not thinking so much in robotics
or querying like physical environments
and thinking more along the lines of
data environment so that's why I was
trying
to understand how we could utilize
this yes yeah you can yeah and uh you
can push it further right you can make a
uh a combination of the two you can make
a uh an environment that flies a drone
uh your agent has to control the Drone
but it can also query the environment
for hey what is going to be my position
in 5 seconds so kind of this this well
abstract action that's basically
querying the environment well since we
have this uh this mechanism that we can
depending on what action you send
correspond or match this with an
observation now you can do stuff like
that there's nobody stopping you doing
it whether or not it's useful for your
agent well that's up to you I I was just
yeah I'm I'm trying to make your
environments as expressive as can or
your the framework as expressive as I
can and yeah you you can you can go wild
with it right you can go
crazy that's perfect because the agent
that I'm kind of that I'm wanting to put
together would need to actually walk
through time in a certain way um and
optimize its activities in a Time series
um yeah and I was I was already
expecting you that's why I brought up
this this uh that's very cool I be very
excited to see uh well whether or not
you uh you can build your environment
and ARS environment would be yeah very
cool
Absolutely I'll keep you updated then
nice
thanks the observable and actor roles in
orx
environments can any entity take on
either of these roles or are there
certain constraints for example
let's say the agent must always have the
actor role or
something no they're completely
unconstrained um there is no real
distinction under the hood
between uh entities or between something
that represents an environment as
something that represents an agent uh
they are both entities in arcs
environments um the only thing is that
you can make uh something which I call
an active or a passive entity by the way
all this terminology it's all up for
discussion I've thought about this and
most of the terms that I come up with
they they don't really fit what I what
I'm trying to say um but an active
entity is something that whenever it
gets an observation or whenever it
receives an action it emits or it at
least considers emitting to uh
subscribers for example the mountain car
uh environment itself would be an active
entity whenever the the agent sends an
action to move the car it will
correspond or it will match this uh this
this action with well moving the car um
whereas the agent whenever it gets an
observation from the environment well it
doesn't really have to do anything we
have to in the later stage attach an
inance process but that is something
that's not ARX environments that is ARX
and first so we we make this entity um
passive in a sense that it it's it's an
observer uh that can also send actions
but those are not triggered by an actual
algorithm that we write ourselves uh in
arxs environments but it's a result of
some inference process it's the triggers
are external to the the reactive
ecosystem that we've built in ARX
environments
itself so that's the only distinction
that I make but you can yeah something
that represents an environment or
something that represents an an agent
they're they're under the hood
completely the same things they are just
uh entities that that that can
communicate with with with external
entities do you think you could um in
addition add a a discrete control space
example for us as well because Mountain
car and the evasion thermostat are both
um continuous
examples even if it's just a simple uh
discrete control space or categorical in
particular categorical control
space maybe a simple maze example or a
grid example you know like the windy
grid that's often used in reinforcement
learning even if it's just a simple
windy
grid windy grid yeah okay I'll I'll
Google
that just uh even if it's just a simple
categorical control space because that's
what our problems currently uh center
around not so much continuous control
spaces but uh categorical control
spaces okay that's uh yeah I can do that
okay I
windy G world yeah okay I I can do
that be
excellent I ask sort of a very quick
broad question about the whole
ontology my when I first learned about
this my own Na and and just sort of
looking through the docs I thought oh
okay this is this is a rapper around RX
and thir for standardizing the creation
of an Environ enironment that you will
then use for for whatever purposes but
it sounds to me it's it's not at all
that it's it's really this is this is
not even really a way of talking about
an environment per se this is no it's
more of a it's a communication protocol
for active inference agents I would say
yeah yeah it's like well you this this
is a way to sort of standardize the the
dietic interaction between you know two
abstract entities U and that could be
between environment and an agent you
know or it could be something else
entirely okay that's much much broader
than what I was conceptualizing ex so I
I when I when I started this indeed I I
started as okay I want to standardize
environment Creation in in our ecosystem
in our fer and I had discussion with
Magnus kudal who's also uh in in this
Discord I saw and well we had some very
interesting talks and he said well
actually an environment and and an agent
they're not so different right they
just they just hand or they just receive
data from each other and and handle them
accordingly so yeah there is a certain
uh symmetry there and then I thought
well if there's a symmetry there then I
can make an
overarching uh programming concept and
just kind of implement it that way and
that's what I did and then it turns from
just a way in which you can make an
agent and an environment communicate to
a in which you can communicate this
whole network
of uh of subscriptions and
Communications um because there's yeah
there's no constraints anymore so for
example we run an environment in in uh
in our lab with MCO actually that um has
well a
non-trivial uh entity interaction where
we have a hearing aid that uh gets data
from both the external world because it
can well it has a microphone and it
should register the external world but
it can also get data from the user of
the hearing aid saying hey I'm happy
with the hearing aid settings yes or no
so now we have a three entity
environment we have the user we have the
hearing aid and we have the uh the
external world that just emits noise
then we have a fourth entity which is
our agent that should learn the
preferences of the user that should get
data from the hearing aid and should uh
tweak the parameters inside of the
hearing a so now we have four entities
that are communicating in this
non-trivial way and well we built this
in arcs environments and it all holds up
like it all just yeah it runs just
because whenever we get data the hearing
aid knows ah I get new data I get new
noise I have to transform this noise and
send it to the user and I have to do a
f8 transform and send it to the agent
for analysis uh and just because it does
this reactively it's all tractable and
all works nicely so yeah uh it it it
turned out to be a bit of a uh a
bigger well scope than I would have
imagined but I'm yeah I I'm I'm not
making any claims on on how large it
actually is that's uh yeah
cool this this is also very cool I'm
very very thankful that you're you're
working on this because I I I had the
thought like oh what what what then is
you know sort of predicated of the
environment it's kind of like what we
have the environment and the Asian
they're kind of both being equally
treated
you it's a very interesting question
right so so what the what is the actual
actual
difference um some people say well an
agent has some sort of inferential
process uh on how it comes up with an
action but in a sense well we are all
all just with our eyes and ears and
muscles we have an interface to to the
environment um but yeah in in in that
sense we we are just all Mark of
blankets with internal states that that
that navigate this world uh and this
well communication that we have with our
outside world I yeah I try to replicate
that
fastic
thanks anyone else want to ask any
questions yeah Kristoff or yeah yeah I
have a question um I I didn't quite get
what you um what you said about the
difference between the typical
reinforcement learning setting and the
RX environments Could you um could you
could you explain that again please that
was very interesting sure sure if if you
want or if you make an environment in JY
in gymnasium we can we can look at
the um at their documentation right so
let's see
gymnasium
package so I go to gymnasium and I want
to make my own custom
environment I saw it here make your own
custom environment i' I've visited this
page before so we can make our
environment blah blah blah and then you
have this function step the step method
usually contains most of the logic for
your environment it accepts an action
computes the state of the environment
after applying that action and returns a
five Tuple observation reward terminated
truncated
info so we write a function step that
takes only an action so this is the main
design Paradigm of JY and most
reinforcement
learning packages actually where I emit
an
action this action is incorporated into
the world um but the time that uh the
environment is uh simulated forward is
constant so there's no notion of
different time intervals whereas if I'm
I'm a very big uh football effici out
for the Americans that's soccer um but
it's actually football but if I kick a
ball I kick the ball the ball starts
rolling
well whether or not I do something the
ball will just continue rolling like
this this environment around me it
doesn't wait for me to emit additional
actions or I'm not consciously saying
okay for the next second I do nothing
and then the ball rolls okay for the
next second I do nothing again and the
ball rolls further no there is a in the
real world there is a difference right
we do something and then the world just
continues
so we can do something at any point in
time and the world around us will just
well the world keeps on turn um and
that's what I was trying to do with with
ARX environments is to um alleviate
ourselves of
this um communication protocol because
this specifies I get one
observation I can do one action per
observation and that's it and in between
uh different observations I have no
power to do anything whatsoever also if
I have an environment that instead of
modeling one second forward I now do
half a second well everything breaks
down because now I have to emit actions
at twice a speed or my observations
don't correspond anymore with my
internal model or there's all kinds of
stuff that if you do it like this it
turns kind of awkward and that's what I
was trying to
alleviate
uh with with ARX environments is that
I'm trying to make this communication
between agent and environment as free as
possible so if you have a hearing aid
environment yeah that you can yeah
that's that that's it if if I'm not yeah
I'm rambling sorry good interrup that's
a good that's a good explanation and U I
think you also mentioned something about
um some difficulty there because uh the
the question then becomes like if you
have multiple agents in with the
environment then what exactly is the
state of the world
right um what exactly is the state of
the world is not uh because you can just
uh sort
of you can have like a god entity that
takes care of of of this stuff that that
that kind of resolves all conflicts in
that sense um the main question for me
would be
well we just took away your one moment
to conduct an action in reinforcement
learning you have one moment you can do
an action and you'll get one observation
we just took away this one moment and
gave you the opportunity to act at any
point in time well when are you going to
do it right so you know the reason I'm
asking about this is that it it
immediately got me thinking about um
stepen wolfram's work on Observer Theory
so he's trying to formalize uh the
notion of an observer right and um there
is this um whole field that he basically
invented uh for the physics project
related to uh which calls multi multi
computation I'm not really deep into um
that yet but it seems some it seems
somehow relevant you know as an agents
interacting with the environment we
effectively sample it precisely because
it keeps rolling as we um do the
internal computation required to um
update our um our generative model in
order to to act so I I think you
stumbled onto something quite quite
profound there um and the question the
question is about this this God God mode
view right like that's a that's an old
question in physics whether there exists
the absolute reference frame or whether
everything is
relative um and yeah just won't say that
you know foot for fault there's there's
some there's some interesting problems
there maybe we can we can talk about it
some sometime I would love to hear your
thoughts about this yeah sure like I'm
I'm very interested in this stuff so as
a as a software developer like I would
advise you in your environments if
you're not dealing with you know
existential stuff that just make a god
state that takes care of this but uh you
make a very good point right so if we
really want to make an accurate
representation of of the world do we
need this God state or because we now
allow our environments
to to alleviate this right we can have
multiple entities that together compose
the environment and that there is some
internal communication between them so
um it does it does open up this like it
doesn't slam it wide open but at least
you know there's a in Dutch you would
say open key yeah so
so I I think there is a there's a that
that's that's a potential um incursion
into effectively resolving some of the
most interesting problems in the
fundamental theories of physics that
understanding precisely which one is the
case whether is this um absolute
reference frame or whether you can just
simply explain everything through these
relative reference frames and agent
sampling the environments and if if you
can effectively recover something that
looks like physics from um this
interaction which is what wall from is
essentially working on that would be
that would be a complete computation of
fundamental Theory of physics and it's a
bit big undertaking but it's worth uh
worth considering not just merely from
you know um software engineering
perspective but from from that angle if
if you're interested in that kind of
stuff I mean yeah it it's very
interesting it's something that I you
you know it's a very big deviation from
what my supervisor wants me to work on
so it's probably not something that I'm
going to undertake but yeah if if anyone
wants to pick it up right who am I to
stop
them thanks it's great work
cool yeah anyone else want to ask any
questions
how would you deal with the setting of
multiple ant nestmates moving around and
modifying the pheromones on the ground
so in these kinds of simulations it's
common enough to have the pherone
phermone state on the ground and then
Nest mates that are reading and writing
how do you deal with the spatial
proximity and the collisions and
interactions
so that is something very very very
difficult I'm working on a project right
now where once again we're modeling
football uh which is why I brought up
this example just now um and like
resoling collisions is something
extremely difficult it's something that
I don't have a standardized uh advised
way of doing an arcs environments just
because game studios uh they they spend
God knows how many developer hours on
resolving collisions efficiently so
that's not something that I think well
we we can figure out in an afternoon
right
um it's it's it's something that would
be in the internal dynamics of your
environment but not something that is
part of your communication protocol per
se just influences the the the type of
observations that your agent would get
um so it's not something that I can give
that I feel qualified to give advice
on but it is like making this
environment with ants running around
the floor that is something that's just
a multi-agent environment that's fully
covered the problem is these these uh
the collisions that is a difficult thing
it's not uh difficult in an arcs
environment uh perspective it's
difficult in a computational geometry
perspective that you want to resolve
collisions that's yeah like in in tripa
a games you can still clip into walls
somewhere
that's that's a great and funny response
yeah I would just highlight the the real
structural difference when you pointed
to the step function in the
gymnasium that yes is why in so often
for these control problems there's like
a null action or like a weight action so
you kind of get this um bodal action
Vector policy Vector where there's like
a do nothing option and then all the
options because out of requirement
something must be emitted at every click
of the simulation and all of a sudden
it's like we mve from walking on a
staircase to like ice skating or flying
with RX and fur because it has totally
opened up a dimension of the control
question when to act not just which with
according to a metronome and that's
that's an entirely different approach
that um the communication protocols
enable and then those communication
protocols can have all these other
functionalities like they can have a
subontology or they can have compliance
features as well so it's super powerful
and we're very excited to learn
it that's yeah that's the main point uh
the yeah it's a two sides of the same
coin like it it opens up this
communication protocol but then yeah you
have to question
when when it's something something that
I'm going to spend time on in my next
project like can we make an iterative
procedure maybe with iterations and ARs
and third we can send intermediate
posteriors and we have we always have
like a an action that we Supply I I
don't know yet I have no idea or I have
ideas but I don't have anything working
yet I think to me the underlying
principle of the RX in first Suite
versus
traditional yes this um
um instead of having synchronized
Communications we now have asynchronized
communications between everything
between everything
yes I'm I'm glad I got that point across
that's that's the point I wanted to
make great well um if anyone else has a
question otherwise we will continue
learning and watching the GitHub updates
and just building out examples CU in the
coming months we know a lot of fun
things will
happen all right yeah um you guys can
always reach out to me on I don't know
GitHub Twitter I don't know how often
I'll check Discord I'll try you know
I'll try um but you can always reach out
to me on uh on LinkedIn Twitter whatever
that's that's all fine
excellent I I do have a a final question
if that's all right um sure just just
with respect to you know future
directions and that kind of thing what's
kind of biggest problem set of problems
what are you kind of looking to do I
know that's a massive thing but is there
anything relatively summited in that
direction that that we could have speak
to for just a second so I'm very
interested in this when to act uh
problem so this to me opens up the door
to a um an agent
that um because we okay so we can now
act at any point in time or at any point
in time um yeah we can send something to
the environment a logical consequence
for me is that at any point in time we
should have an action ready to send so
when the next observation comes in we
don't know when that's going to be we
should be able to act so we have a
certain computational budget between one
observation and the next we don't know
how much it's going to be but we do have
a budget to spend so I want to design
indeed an interative procedure that
comes up with an action and then refines
it and refines it and refines it until
well the next observation comes in so we
we have to send whatever we had and we
get the the next observation this gives
you if this all works right this gives
you a very nice robust agent that if you
give it a lot of computing power a lot
of computational budget then in between
observations well it's going to be able
to come up with a pretty good um pretty
good action and will solve the task
accordingly like ideally however if you
limit this uh uh this computational
budget you put it on like a Raspberry Pi
or on an edge device it will not have as
much iterations to refine its actions so
it will still solve the problem
hopefully but it will be less efficient
doing so it will be slightly Dum so this
is a very to me is a very interesting
problem to think about because then you
have a sort of a a procedure for control
that is robust to loss of computation or
whatever and it's still adaptive and
reactive and and and all those nice
things we get from from Asian
inference um so yeah that's something
that I that I would want to work on if I
you know at 48 hours in a
day it's very interesting so it sounds
to me like a number of iterations you
just refer to as um the iteration field
in the call of the infer function yes in
infer yes if I can do something like
that so I run an indefinite amount of
iterations and I just stop the inference
procedure whenever I have to do
something and then I extract the latest
posterior for the action and I I send
that to the environment yeah that's
something well that would be the first
thing I would
investigate yeah I I think it has the
potential to make the behavior in
general quite robust if you if you
consider that
approach it yeah it would be rob it
would always have something to do do
like it would always do something
whether or not sort of the the the free
energy would converge uh or yeah as as a
measure of whether or not this action is
good enough uh that is to be
investigated but it would allow us to
run the same models on edge devices as
well and get slightly worse performance
but
still yeah yeah it would still do the
job we and then you can investigate you
know how many iterations do I actually
need before I can solve the problem uh
it's of course problem dependent but
yeah it's a very yeah it's just
something that that really interest me I
really like this this way of thinking um
and it's in part why I why I wrote this
package because I I don't like this this
this synchronized communication protocol
from Jim I just I just don't like it
yeah that's why I wrote wrote ARS
environments I think the only
alternative is to not be able to respond
whenever it gets an ation other words to
postpone your
response it NES back into the um the the
synchronicity approach again so it
breaks away from the you know the
reactiveness of
the but then you you run into the
robustness issue I would say if you have
a self-driving car and it it's driving
into a wall because it's thinks it's a
green light because those things are not
that that smart nowadays uh and ah it
figures out it's a wall but it takes
some time to adjust or it takes some
time to come up with the idea okay now I
have fully converged on the action that
I have to steer away well by that time
we might have already crashed into the
wall um so this this queuing up of uh uh
of observations and waiting until uh my
computation is fully converged I think
it takes away the robustness like if you
if if you don't have enough
computational budget to
spend well yeah you you might do the
wrong thing it's the same as when you
and I are in a car right if we're in a
very
um a very busy situation so well I'm in
the Netherlands so we have cyclist right
so if we have cyclists we have other
cars and there's a an ambulance coming
what it's very busy you might feel
overwhelmed but you still kind of know
the basic things to do to to to steer
your car it's basically the same where
you have limited computational budget
there's all this stuff around you so to
come up with a really thought through
response or action uh it's too much to
ask because you don't have the
computational budget but your brain kind
of prioritizes and says well if we stay
on the road and we let the ambulance
pass and well we're fine for now we're
this is the best we can do um so this
feeling of being overwhelmed by what
what goes on on around you inspired this
idea of of robustness and uh uh of
interruptibility
basically yeah but then again how how
how I'm going to do it well no idea yet
or run run our iner iterations and see
if I can uh can send intermediate
posterior results or something or but
it's just something yeah I I find this
very very very
interesting think it's a good thing that
free energy in
general decays uh predictably in a sense
so I mean just fully using your budget
your computational budget for that time
that you're allow before the next
observation
arrives I think it's it's fairly safe to
just uh yes use the current value of the
posterior that's the best you can do the
circumstances yes that that that would
be the argument
indeed hopefully hopefully this this
this opens up the road to having actual
you know robots driving around instead
because
well there's no self-driving cars where
I live there's no robots or drones
flying around and I think one of the
reasons is because they're not robust or
interruptible
fly agreed
yeah all right thank you all we'll look
forward to staying updated
asynchronously even asynchronously
reactively see y all soon
bye thanks